Finding aid for Mike Wallace CBS/60 Minutes Papers, 1922-2007
Bentley Historical Library
Mike Wallace CBS/60 Minutes papers
1922-2007
1968-2007
Bentley Historical Library
Wallace, Mike, 1918-2012
03171 Aa 2; UAm
176 linear feet
1 oversize volume
1 oversize folder
Papers of Mike Wallace (1918-2012), broadcast journalist; CBS News correspondent; co-founder and correspondent on CBS 60 Minutes news program from 1968 to 2006. The collection comprises 60 Minutes program files, including transcripts of the broadcasts and interviews with participants, viewer correspondence, background research, newspaper clippings and photographs, and story ideas in various stages of development that were dropped or never aired. General files consisting of Wallace's personal and professional materials covering his responsibilities within CBS News beyond 60 Minutes, notably his work covering the war in Vietnam and political campaigns in the 1960s and 1970s. The general files include speeches, awards and personal correspondence. Photographs and other visual materials, sound recordings, and biographical materials.
The Mike Wallace collection is on deposit from CBS-News (donor no. 7115 ) and came to the library in multiple accessions, 2001-2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The Mike Wallace CBS/ 60 Minutes collection is on deposit from CBS News and access and use is subject to certain conditions stipulated by CBS.
The Mike Wallace CBS/ 60 Minutes collection is open to research except for select files which are closed until December 1, 2030, by CBS News as a condition that the collection could come to the Bentley Library. These files are listed in the finding aid but filed separately from the boxes of open material. Files closed to research are indicated as "Closed until December 1, 2030" in the folder listing.
Researchers must secure the prior written permission of CBS News to publish or excerpt any of the CBS Papers or part thereof. As part of the agreement between CBS News, Mike Wallace, and the University of Michigan, researchers will need to read and sign the "Addendum to Researcher Registration Form for Researchers Using 'The Mike Wallace/CBS News 60 Minutes Papers' Deposited at the Bentley Historical Library." Researcher can submit requests via permission request form.
Researchers will note that no copying in any form of items within the Mike Wallace CBS/ 60 Minutes will be permitted.
The Mike Wallace CBS/ 60 Minutes collection is a combination of CBS News files and Mike Wallace Personal Materials. The Personal Materials, a much smaller part of the total collection, is indicated in the container listing with an asterisk (*).
Mike Wallace was born Myron Leon Wallace on May 9, 1918 in Brookline, Massachusetts to Russian Jewish immigrants family. He graduated from Brookline High School in 1935 then attended the University of Michigan where he had opportunity to work as an announcer at the University's radio division. After graduating in 1939 with a BA degree, Wallace began his broadcasting career first at Grand Rapids, Mich. WOOD-WASH radio station, and then at Detroit's WXYZ, where his work included newscasting as well as narration on The Green Hornet.
In 1941 Wallace was hired by the Chicago Sun's radio station as a newscaster, but soon wartime service as a naval communications officer interrupted his career. After the war, he went to work as a news reporter for radio station WMAQ Chicago. He first joined CBS in 1951 then left the network in 1955 to pursue other opportunities. He worked steadily with numerous television credits including Night Beat (1956-57) and The Mike Wallace Interview (1957-60) and the Peabody Award-winning public affairs series Biography (1959-61). He returned to CBS in 1963 where he became a staff correspondent (1963-2006) and anchored The CBS Morning News (1963-66). At CBS Wallace was political correspondent and a floor reporter at the Democratic and Republican conventions in the 1960s and 1970s.
In 1968 CBS News executive producer Don Hewitt, with co-editors Mike Wallace and Harry Reasoner, launched 60 Minutes. Premiering on September 24, the program was a weekly newsmagazine that revolutionized television news programming. In at the beginning, Wallace continued to work on the program until his retirement in 2006.
Throughout his career, Wallace has been the recipient of numerous broadcasting awards and honors. In 1996 he won the Robert F. Kennedy Journalism Award grand prize and television first prize for a CBS Reports broadcast "In the Killing Fields of America" (January 1995), a three-hour report he co-anchored on violence in America. His other professional honors include 21 Emmy Awards, five Alfred I. duPont-Columbia University Awards, five George Foster Peabody Awards, a Robert E. Sherwood Award, a Paul White Award (1991), a Distinguished Achievement Award from the University of Southern California School of Journalism and a Robert F. Kennedy Journalism Award in the international broadcast category.
Wallace was elected a fellow of the Society of Professional Journalists, Sigma Delta Chi (November 1975) and was awarded a doctorate in humane letters, honoris causa, from the University of Massachusetts (1978). In May 1987 he received an honorary doctorate of laws from the University of Michigan and, in 1989 an honorary doctorate of laws from the University of Pennsylvania.
In June of 1991 he was inducted into the Television Academy Hall of Fame. In 1993 he was named the Broadcaster of the Year by the International Radio and Television Society. Part of his rich legacy includes the Knight-Wallace Fellowship and Mike and Mary Wallace House at the University of Michigan. Wallace's donations support this in-residence study program begun in 1994 for professional journalists seeking to improve their knowledge in a desired field or issue.
Wallace was a popular speaker on the lecture circuit and author of several books. His book Mike Wallace Asks, a compilation of interviews from "Night Beat" and "The Mike Wallace Interview," was published in 1958 and his memoir Close Encounter, co-authored with Gary Paul Gates, was published in September 1984. In 2002 his book Medal of Honor: Profiles of America's Military Heroes from the Civil War to the Present co-authored with Allen Mikaelian, was published.
Mike Wallace died at his home in Canaan, CT on April 7, 2012 at age 93.
Summary Contents List
60 Minutes
Program Files, 1968-2007
Boxes 1-45, 106-121, 157-158, 166-169, 172
Dead Stories Files
Boxes 48-51
Background Files
Boxes 122-130, 150-152, 155-156, 158-159
Viewer Correspondence
Boxes 131-132, 159
Miscellaneous Story Ideas (By Producer)
Boxes 133, 159-160, 173
Collected transcripts
Box 46-47, 160, 173
General Files
Boxes 52-92, 134-146, 160-164
Personal/Biographical
Boxes 93, 147-149, 164, 170-171, 175-176
Visual Materials
Photographs, Box 94, 164, 175-176
Videotapes, Boxes 95-97, 154
Sound Recordings
Box 153
Litigation
Boxes 98-105, 164
The Mike Wallace CBS/ 60 Minutes Papers document the career and associated activities of one of television news's most influential broadcasters. The collection currently spans a thirty-five year career at CBS News and includes program files, correspondence, speeches, writings, memoranda, photographs, and other materials relating to Wallace's work as co-editor of 60 Minutes and as principal correspondent of various other CBS documentaries. The papers range broadly, covering both his activities within CBS as well as within the larger broadcast community. The collection has been largely maintained in the series established by Wallace and his staff. These series are: Program Files; General Files; Personal/Biographical; Visual Materials; and Litigation Files.
The Mike Wallace CBS/ 60 Minutes collection is a combination of CBS News files and Mike Wallace Personal Materials. The Personal Materials, a much smaller part of the total collection, is indicated in container listing with an asterisk (*).
60 minutes (Television program); Television broadcasting -- United States.; Television broadcasting of news -- United States.; Television journalists -- United States.; 60 minutes (Television program); Television broadcasting of news -- United States.; Radio programs.; Green Hornet (Radio program); Information please (Radio program); Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.; Wallace, Mike, 1918-2012.; CBS News.; Wallace, Mike, 1918-2012.; CBS News.; Wallace, Mike, 1918-2012.
- 60 Minutes Program Files
  The Program Files series is the largest in the collection and dates from 1968 (when 60 Minutes premiered) to 2007 and is arranged by television schedule years (beginning in September). The content of the Program Files has changed over time and this accounts for some of the subseries that were developed with the passage of time. For the first few years, these files consisted only of the transcripts of the program as aired. Whatever background information was collected or if any post-program material was received, these were usually filed with the collection's General Files (described below). Beginning around 1975, the Program Files began to include, in addition to the broadcast transcript, all of the materials (clippings, articles, producer memoranda, viewer suggestions, transcripts of interviews with participants, etc.) accumulated in connection with the background preparation for any given story. Responses to stories, such as update information, viewer correspondence, and newspaper articles, were also now included in the individual program file. This post-program materials would remain with Program Files until the 1986/87 season when it was transferred again to the General Files.
  An important subseries of the Program Files consists of story ideas in various stages of development that were dropped or never aired for whatever reason. Initially, this subseries was designated as "Dead Story" materials and covered the period from 1981 to 1990. Included were clippings, correspondence, and memoranda from producers and others with suggestions for possible program segments. Prior to 1981, story suggestion files were usually maintained as part of the General Files series. Around 1990, the content of the Program Files series again changed and thus was created a subseries of background materials for stories both aired and proposed. Because there is often overlap between the program file and the background file for a given story in the 1990s, the researcher is encouraged to consult both.
  Concluding the Program Files is a set of binders containing copies of transcripts for 60 Minutes and other Mike Wallace programs such as CBS Reports and his Biography program. This portion of the collection only covers the period up to 1990.
  - Season I, September 1968-July 1969
    [Permission required for use, see Access and Use section for details.]
    - "Nixon"; "Humphrey" (Hubert Humphrey); "Cops" (Attorney General Ramsey Clark), September 24, 1968 (Box 1)
    - "Gas Warfare"; "Nixon,", October 8, 1968 (Box 1)
    - "Germ Warfare"; "Wallace" (George Wallace), October 22, 1968 (Box 1)
    - "Nixon"; "DeGaulle" (Jean-Jacques Servan-Schreiber, publisher of L'Express), November 12, 1968 (Box 1)
    - "Muskie" (Edmund Muskie), November 26, 1968 (Box 1)
    - "Prison Assaults" (investigation of sexual assaults in Philadelphia prison system, and interview with Arlen Specter); "International Money Game" (international monetary crisis), December 10, 1968 (Box 1)
    - "Martin Luther King's Family at Christmas"; "Illiteracy" (Adult illiteracy), December 24, 1968 (Box 1)
    - "Spiro Agnew,", January 7, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Middle East Crisis,", January 21, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Airplane Hijacking"; "Homicide,", February 4, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "The Welfare Mess, Country-Style" (Mississippi County, Arkansas); "Daniel Cohn-Bendit" (French student revolutionary), February 18, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Carnegie Hall for the Hip" (Rock concert hall Fillmore East and producer Bill Graham); "Analysis of Nixon Press Conference" (Bill Moyers, Emmet Hughes, Michel de St. Pol), March 4, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Welfare in the City" (Baltimore, Maryland); "John Mitchell" (Attorney General), March 18, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Tora, Tora, Tora" (controversy over Hollywood movie about Pearl Harbor filmed with US Navy help); "American Draft Resisters Living in Canada,", May 13, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Nigeria and Biafra"; "German Measles Vaccine,", June 10, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "American Detention Camps" (1950 McCarran Detention Camp Law), June 24, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Highlights I,", July 8, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Highlights II,", July 22, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Season II, September 1969-September 1970
    - "You're Getting Rich on My Land" (Alaska, oil, and Native Alaskans); "Military Punishment" (Marine Corps Camp Pendleton sweatboxes and the case of Stanley Luzcko), September 16, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Rehabilitation of Vietnam Amputees,", September 30, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "The Brig at Camp Pendleton"; "McCarthy's Views on Vietnam" (Eugene McCarthy), October 14, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Interview with Bishop Fulton J. Sheen,", October 28, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Draft Lawyers" (legal draft avoidance); "Ireland"; "Zebra: Black Advertising Agency,", November 11, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Examination of Vice-President Agnew's criticism of television news,", November 25, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Judge Clement F. Haynsworth" (rejected Nixon nominee to Supreme Court), December 9, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Suicide and its Prevention"; "The Mott Millionaire" (Stewart Mott), December 16, 1969 (Box 1)
    - "Eldridge Cleaver and the Black Panther Party,", January 6, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Law enforcement in Washington, DC,", January 20, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Revolution in the Movies" (young moviegoers), February 3, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Gun Control" (Federal Gun Control film What It's All About), February 17, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "The Four Billion Dollar Torpedo" (M-48 Torpedo), March 3, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Auto Bumpers,", March 24, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Cairo" (examination of Egypt and the Middle East War), March 31, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "We're Drowning in Garbage,", April 14, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Who is Bernie Cornfeld?" (financial wizard); "Bill of Rights interviews (Senator Barry Goldwater, Yale Law Professor Alexander Bickel, Trial lawyer Edward Bennett Williams), April 28, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Secretary of the Interior and Mrs. Walter Hickel"; "Attorney General and Mrs. John Mitchell (John and Martha Mitchell) (no transcript; see repeat, 5/20/73), May 12, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Tricia Nixon's Tour of the White House"; "My Lai" (Frank McGee and Seymour Hersh debate), May 26, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "A Cry for Help" (child abuse); "B-1 Bomber,", June 9, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Vietnam Coming and Going,", June 16, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Highlights I,", August 18, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Highlights II,", September 1, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Season III, September 1970-June 1971
    - "If Cable TV Comes to Your House,", September 15, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Profile of William F. Buckley"; "Cuba" (speech by Fidel Castro), September 29, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Profile of Dr. Henry Kissinger,", October 13, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "China's Bomb" (nuclear development in China), October 27, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Servan-Schreiber on DeGaulle" (Jean-Jacques Servan-Schreiber, publisher of L'Express); "Marijuana Harvest in Kansas,", November 10, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Interview with Walter Hickel" (Secretary of the Interior); "Aaron Copeland at 70,", November 24, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Black and White Army" (Racial tension and violence in the US military in Germany); "Interview with Canadian Prime Minister Pierre Trudeau,", December 8, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "Dangerous Toys" (unsafe children's toys); "James J. Kilpatrick"; "Renaissance" (Drug rehabilitation program in Westport, Connecticut), December 22, 1970 (Box 1)
    - "A National Scandal" (Federal Housing Authority); "Jews Behind the Iron Curtain" (Bucharest, Romania), January 5, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Notes from the Underground" (underground newspapers); Nicholas Von Hoffman's critique of "Notes from the Underground,", January 19, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Early Spiro Agnew,", February 2, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "A National Scandal" (FHA in Spokane, Washington); "Profile of Ron Lyle" (heavyweight boxer), March 2, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "How to Succeed in the PX Business Without Really Trying" (William Crum, military retail post exchange system), March 16, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Report on the Tobacco Industry,", March 30, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Moshe Dayan" (Israeli Defense Minister); "Golda Meir" (Israeli Prime Minister); "Aharon Yariv" (Israeli Army General); "The Bottle Generation" (alcoholism on the job), April 13, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Can You Avoid a Heart Attack?", April 27, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Tour of the Lyndon B. Johnson Library"; "Mark-48 Torpedo--Update" (M-48), May 11, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Tankers and Tycoons" (report on the oil tanker business in the Middle East); "Interview with Eugene McCarthy,", May 25, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Pension Plans"; "Highlights,", June 8, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Season IV, September 1971-June 1972
    - "South Vietnamese Elections" (interviews with Vice President Ky and General Duong Van Minh); "Business Conventions,", September 19, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Lost Property" (the inconsistency of property tax), September 26, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Nippon Steel" (Japanese and US steel industries compared); "Cry Baby" (diagnosis of infant ailments through voice print analysis); "American emigrants in London,", October 11, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Cosmetic Surgery"; "Nixon's Supreme Court Nominees,", October 21, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "New Towns" (Sweden), October 31, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Prostitution"; "Go Fight City Hall" (Berkeley, California); "Election Results" (mayoral elections in Boston, Philadelphia, and Cleveland, and Mississippi gubernatorial election), November 2, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Not to My Kid, You Don't" (Congressional children and busing in Washington, DC); "See It Now" (twentieth anniversary of first broadcast), November 14, 1971 (Box 2)
    - "Earthquake" (San Francisco, California), November 25, 1971 (Box 2)
    - "John Connally and the GOP."; "Reverend Hosea Williams" (SCLC leader's visits to China and meetings with Chou En-lai), November 28, 1971 (Box 2)
    - "Amnesty, Who Wants It?" (Vietnam draft resisters and deserters), December 12, 1971 (Box 2)
    - "POW Wives" (The Bombing and the POWs); "Cotton Bowl: A Footnote" (Cotton Bowl stadium evictees in Dallas, Texas), January 2, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "The Berrigan Case" (Fathers Philip and Daniel Berrigan, the Harrisburg Eight, and the Anti-war movement); "Japanese Americans,", January 9, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Clifford Irving" (Howard Hughes biography); "Can Anybody Beat Muskie?" (Democratic contenders in 1972 elections), January 16, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "100,000 Deserters" (Vietnam), January 23, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Credit Card Thievery,", January 30, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Clifford Irving" (Elmer de Hory film; Howard Hughes biography hoax), February 6, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Tour of Air Force One"; "Meany v. Nixon" (Interview with George Meany, AFL-CIO President), February 13, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Interview with Georgi Arbatov" (Gyorgyi Arbatov of Moscow's USA Institute, on Nixon in China); "Qaddafi" (El-Qaddafi, ruler of Libya), February 27, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Italian Repatriates,", March 5, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "An Enemy of the People" (whistleblower Henry Durham and the Lockheed C-5A); "Jack Anderson,", March 12, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Vietnam Amputees-Update"; "Clifford Irving, Actor of the Year" (Howard Hughes biography hoax), March 19, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Meany and the President" (George Meany, AFL-CIO President, and conflict with President Nixon), March 26, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Dita Beard" (ITT and Chilean government scandal); "Death with Dignity" (euthanasia), April 2, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "The Unrealized Promise of Safe Streets" (L.E.A.A., Federal agency giving money to local law enforcement to fight crime); "Bobby Fischer" (US chess champion), April 9, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "The Great Train Robberies,", April 16, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Madame Nguyen Thi Binh" (Foreign Minister of the Viet Cong); "Jean-Claude Duvalier" (Baby Doc, Haiti's New President), April 23, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Company Town" (St. Mary's, Georgia mill town, and rape), May 7, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Abortion"; "The George Wallace Phenomenon" (Presidential campaign), May 14, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Family Crisis Intervention Unit,", May 21, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Transcript (no Mike Wallace stories; Wallace reads headlines and mail), June 11, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "When You Wish Upon a Star" (Impact of Disney World on Orange County, Florida), June 18, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Season V, October 1972-September 1973
    - "Papadopoulos and the USA" (Alliance between Greece's military dictatorship and the US), October 1, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "MGM-Death of the Backlot"; "Kissinger,", November 26, 1972 (Box 2)
    - The Heroin Route into the US from Turkey through France (no title), December 10, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "...Your Tired, Your Poor, Your Huddled Masses..." (Illegal aliens and the INS Border Patrol), December 24, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "A Place in the Sun" (US Naval Base at Guantanamo Bay, Cuba); "Water, Water Everywhere" (long show, West Coast only; no transcript; see show, 1/14/73), December 31, 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Welfare for the Rich" (tax shelters), January 7, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "Heads They Win, Tails You Lose!" (Paradise Island Casino in the Bahamas); "Water, Water Everywhere" (water rights in California), January 14, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "Good-by [sic], Saigon" (self-exiled South Vietnamese); "Vietnam: Whose War?" repeat (interview with LBJ, original air date: May 11, 1971), January 28, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "The Selling of Col. Herbert" (Lt. Col. Anthony Herbert and the Vietnam War), February 4, 1973 (Box W3)
      [Closed until December 01, 2030 ]
    - "Coming Home" (Vietnam POW wives); "All-American Family" (Synar family of Muskogee, Oklahoma), February 11, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "Fountain of Youth?" (Gerovital); "What Happened to Ron Lyle" (heavyweight boxer), February 18, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "The Eagleton Syndrome" (depression); "Geisha" (geisha today), February 25, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "Trident: Do We Need It?" (US Navy's nuclear submarine development program); "Hollywood Speak With Forked Tongue" (Hollywood's depiction of Native Americans), March 4, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "Is This Any Way to Run a Railroad?" (the future of Amtrak); "Mardi Gras: The British View,", March 11, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "Vox Pop" (Governor Nelson Rockefeller at town meetings); "The Gypsies" (Gypsies in Romania), March 18, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "What About Public Television?,", March 25, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "Captain Walter Wilber, USN" (anti-war former Vietnam POW); "Welfare for the Rich?" Part II (Ross Perot, Wilbur Mills, Stewart Mott), April 1, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "Tom Benton is 84" (Thomas Hart Benton, American painter), April 8, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "Conversation with a Dead Guerrilla" (PLO spokesman Kamal Nasser, filmed three days before his assassination), April 15, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "Paris Was Yesterday" (Paris in the and New Yorker journalist Janet Flanner, a.k.a. Genet); "Acupuncture" (in China), 1920s; April 22, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "The Short, Unhappy Life of Rover" (pet population explosion in the US); "Hitler Was Here?" (interest in Hitler), April 29, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "Can Cancer Be Prevented?", May 6, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "John and Martha" repeat (original air date: May 12, 1970); "Palestine: A Nation in Exile" (the Black September movement), May 20, 1973 (Box 2)
    - The Heroin Route into the US from Turkey through France repeat (original air date: December 10, 1972), May 27, 1973 (Box 2)
    - "Where There's a Will" (the high cost of probate court); "Tankers and Tycoons" repeat (original air date: May 28, 1971), June 3, 1973 (Box 2)